do you like to wear a band around your
knees during squats and hip thrust maybe
you've been told it's ineffective you've
been shamed on social media and you quit
doing so well I'm Brett contris PhD
personal trainer of 28 years cscs and
I'm here to tell you that it is okay to
do so at the moment wearing a band
around your knees is evidence-based Yes
you heard that right according to the
research you should probably be wearing
a band around your knees if your goal is
to maximize your glute size in this
video I'm going to go through the
evidence there's six applicable studies
so I'm going to roll through those then
I'm going to tell you why I think that
knee bands booty bands get a lot of hate
in the industry and I'm going to wrap
things up with what future research
needs to look at in order to have a
better understanding on this topic part
one the existing body of evidence So
currently there are six studies worth
mentioning involving mini bands glute
Loops pertaining to glut now five of
them involve squats and one of them
involves hip drust and glute Bridges now
let's talk about what research we don't
have we have no studies examining
adductor EMG activity to determine
whether adductor involvement reduces
when you put a band around your knees
and that's important to know and finally
we have no hypertrophy studies no
longitudinal training studies examining
actual glute hypertrophy actual glute
growth looking at glute Siz before and
after a training intervention because
after all that's what we're interested
in glute hypertrophy so when you're in
this situation and you have zero
evidence looking at actual hypertrophy
then we have to go down the list of
mechanistic research and form our
argument using biomechanical rationale
unfortunately that's the best we can do
so let's dive into the sixth study the
first study is titled sex difference in
lower limb electromyography and
kinematics when using resistance bands
during a barbell back squat this
experiment looked at trained individuals
it had them squat with a five rep max
they did three reps of a five rep max
using three different progressively
stronger bands around the knees now as
you can see in this chart glute medius
activity significantly increased now
glute Max activity looks like it's
slightly increased as well but quad
hamstring activity was unchanged and
unfortunately they didn't look at
adductor so let's move on to the next
study this one was titled looped elastic
resistance during squats how do band
position and stiffness affect
myoelectric activity now this study
didn't use loaded squats it looked at
body weight squats so there was no load
no barbell on the back but they did use
three straights of bands so lighter
moderate and heavy and what you'll see
here is as the band tension increased
glute medius and glute Maximus increased
and it looks like women activate the
glutes even higher than men do when
using bands around the knees so let's
dive into the next study this one is
titled looped band placed around thighs
increases EMG of gluteal muscles without
hindering performance during squatting
now in my opinion this is the second
most important study on this topic it
took Advanced lifters they performed
back squats with 80% of their one rep
maximum in addition to reps to failure
with 60% of one rep max so two different
tasks five reps of 80% of 1 RM and then
60% of 1 RM to failure so what you'll
see is the bands significantly increased
glute medius and glute Maximus activity
and it did so without hindering squat
performance now I would think especially
with Advanced lifters like if I put a
band around my knees and squatted with
60% of on RM so if you can squat 500 lb
picture squatting 300 lb for Max reps
how can putting a band around your knees
not reduce the Reps you perform but in
this study it didn't in fact the group
wearing the banner on their knees got
one more rep so it not only didn't hit
iner performance the group wearing the
banner on their knees got one more wrap
so in this study would be pretty
apparent if you got one more wrap and
all those reps had increased glute
activation how could that not lead to
Greater glute growth glute activation
went up even more with the lighter load
group in fact you see a 20% increase in
glute activation wearing the bands
during the 60% one R max squat to me
that sounds pretty promising for the
banded group again this wasn't a
training study it did measure glute
hypertrophy but all we can do is go off
biomechanical rationale this study is
definitely two thumbs up for the banded
group now I'm going to discuss what I
feel is the most important study on this
topic this was conducted by Kennedy
published in 2023 the title is effects
of ban resistant abduction on muscle
activity between the barbell hip thrust
and barbell glute Bridge so this study
also looked at train lifters they did
five rep max hip thrust and glute
Bridges so these are really heavy hip
thrust and glute Bridges I would like to
see another study using lighter loads
cuz this is heavy hip thrusting and
glute bridging what I love about this
study Kennedy the main researcher he
utilized a BC strength glute Loop in the
studies it was really cool they used a
large extra large regular which I think
was the perfect call for trained male
lifters and it was really cool cuz they
used the C break the band I'm going to
start using that in my training now they
did say break the band at the top of the
rep I would love to see a future study
look at break the band at the bottom of
a rep which I'll explain later now let's
talk about this study's findings they
did show that trained subjects were
around 10% weaker when putting the bands
around the knees so creating
simultaneous hip abduction torque
reduces the weight you can use during
hip extension however with the lighter
loads it was not accompanied by reduced
EMG activity of the glutes in fact the
lower glute Max was the same same lower
glute Max activity when using the bands
even with 10% lighter loads but upper
glute Max activity was higher and
interestingly glute medius activity was
lower so this study shows that with hip
thrust and glute Bridges you don't wear
a band to increase glut medius activity
even though the cue was break the bands
at the top that's frontal plain hip
abduction you'd think you'd be pushing
out at the top maximally and that would
be carried out by the glut medius IM
Minimus that was not reflected in the
study you got reduced glut medius EMG
activity but you got increased upper
glus Maximus activity which could be a
big deal so if you have the same range
of motion the same form same stretch on
the muscle in this case the glutes and
you have more activation in one scenario
versus the other one would think that
has to lead to more hypertrophy if all
else is held constant the variation with
a greater EMG activity should lead to
more hypertrophy we need a hypertrophy
study to examine that now the
researchers didn't look at adductor EMG
activity but they did propose that it
would probably reduce and if that does
in fact happen that's a big deal because
for people trying to grow their glutes
without growing their legs this would be
a GameChanger or at least a wise and
valuable strategy and although 10% load
reduction isn't that big of a deal that
equates to you know 50 lbs if your hip
thrust around 500 lb that is less
pressure on the hips which can become a
problem for a lot of my female clients
so if you get bruised up you'll take
every little bit of load reduction you
can if it's not going to compromise
glute activity two more studies not that
valuable but I'm going to mention them
this one's called effects of a band loop
on lower extremity muscle activity and
kinematics during the barbell squat so
this study looked at trained and
untrained individuals that had him do
body weight squats and three rep max
squats with and without loops around
their knees now in general wearing a
band in increased glute activation and
it didn't impact performance it didn't
cause them to use reduced loading just
like the other study I mentioned it did
not negatively impact squat performance
and also didn't impact the knee width so
the knees did not cave in when using the
band and then the final study I'm going
to discuss the title is barbell back
squat how do resistance bands affect
muscle activation and knee kinematics
this looked at semi-trained participants
they squatted with 40% of one rep max
and 80% of one rep max and they used two
different strengths of bands now I want
to look at the lighter load the 40% load
the glute activation went up 25% when
using the stronger bands and that's huge
that's a big different but the bands did
cause greater knee valgas they caused
the knees to cave in a little bit more
some people believe that could impair
squat technique over time but even when
the knees cave in a little bit because
the bands are super strong it still
increases glute activation and here's an
example to check out you can see in the
middle there is no resistance at the
bottom is the EMG signal with light
resistance and at the top is the EMG
signal with heavy resistance all right
now we're going to dive into part two
why all the hate why do booty bands get
such a bad rap in our industry hey if
you're trying to build an absolute dump
truck of a rear end these things don't
do
[__] oh brother this guy stinks I
believe that this hate comes from five
different reasons which I'll touch upon
briefly the first is this newer fallacy
hardcore lifters they like to think that
their way is best the way they learned
is best nothing new will ever be good
everything new that comes out is just a
fad you know these types old school is
best and well I get it I get it I look
at the way bodybuilders trained back in
the 9s I look at the way Arnold trained
it's still amazing to this day but we do
get better case and point look at the
glute Evolution I've created when I
brought hip thrust onto the scene and
all the glute bridge and hip thrust
variations now look at all the plate
loaded and selectorized hip thrust
machines that are cropping up in gyms
all over and you see much greater glute
development it used to be very rare to
see someone with really nice glutes in
the gym now it's very common glute
training has absolutely gotten way
better throughout the decades but I do
get it hardcore Meat Heads don't like
new things and bands are new and so
people automatically assume that they're
silly the second reason is because they
involve glutes and women glutes are
still a taboo Topic in male bodybuilding
it's bizarre if you follow me on
Instagram I typically call out male
bodybuilders for bashing hip thrust and
saying things like if you do hip thrust
and you're a man you should be very
embarrassed and who wants to you know
hump the air doing hip thrust or if you
do hip thrust and you're a man take your
tampon out guys TR glutes as hard as
they never did us like it to me I got
into bodybuilding like I want Tom
platz's legs I want this guy's arms I
never said oh I want that guy's ass all
right Chris we got we got we got
approval for that cuz let me tell you
are we going to be okay to put that one
up as a short yes you can yes okay if
you're doing hip frosters and you're a
man go change your T like those are
things heard even in 2025 you notice the
muscle magazines they never talk about
glutes I have a book from 1924 they
didn't talk about glutes now it's 101
years later and they still don't talk
about glutes it's always been this way
in male bodybuilding in female physique
training super girls are all about the
glut it's this strange opposite world
but also body bilding has a lot of male
chauvinist and a lot of Dunning Krueger
effect a lot of bullies are attracted to
bodybuilding and these guys bully and
they mansplain and they assume that
women in the gym are just so flighty and
they couldn't possibly figure out a
better method than what they do in the
gym and it's so bizarre because they
will tell you to train legs one day a
week and just do squats and don't ever
use bands and don't do Kickbacks and
don't do hip thrust and they'll tell you
to train the way they do which they
decide to look at the human body and say
I'm going to break up the upper body
into four or five different days and I'm
would do all lower body together in one
session well a woman might look at the
human body and go I'm going to do all
upper body in one session and break the
lower body up into several different
sessions if you're training glutes and
legs 3 days a week you're on the right
track do not listen to men they do not
care about glute development the way you
do they will typically give you terrible
advice for glute building most of them
have never done a single set of hip
thrust they've never done a cable
Kickback they've never done the seated
hip abduction machine they've never put
a booty band on and done a set of
abduction or kickbacks they are not the
experts on this matter women are so they
have massing Dunning keger effect they
will give bizarrely hypocritical advice
like don't isolate the glutes and then I
wish I could be the woman in this
situation and some Meatheads said quit
doing that silly exercise I say why well
just squat well why this isolates the
glutes you don't need to do isolation
work for the glutes oh really do you do
pec deck do you do flies yeah do you do
curls for your biceps yeah do you do
tricep extension for your triceps do you
do side delt work yeah you do cab raises
yeah you do leg extensions leg curls
yeah you do shrugs you do lap prayers so
what you're telling me it's good to
isolate every single muscle in the body
except the glutes and then I just be
like you're so stupid I can't even take
you seriously bye-bye but women are too
nice in the gym probably a good thing
that doesn't happen but I do wish women
could be more assertive and let the
silly bro know how hypocritical his
advice is all right moving on to point
number three bands work the squeeze
there's a large body of evidence I have
every single study I'm actually
preparing for a presentation on this
topic in general exercises that work you
in the stretch position position are
more effective at growing muscle so a
lot of This research has emerged on
different body parts but the problem is
not all studies show this there's more
nuance and with glutes we don't know yet
right now we have the Plotkin 2023 study
showing that hipos and squats tied for
glute growth hip dos work you more in
the squeeze squats more in the stretch
so these bands don't work you in the
stretch and they work you all in the
squeeze so they're looked at as a bad
thing is something that's going to be
very ineffective for glute growth here's
the deal during the co quarantine my
girls were calling me tell me my upper
glutes are growing you know I think I'm
building my upper glutes because they're
using their glute Loops every single day
they're bored to death they're doing all
the band standing hip abduction they're
doing their glute medus Kickbacks with
the band they're doing Kickbacks they're
doing abduction and kickbacks from all
the different angles and they upper
glutes are growing so if the bands cause
you to train at home or let's say you
get to the end of your leg work and
you're like I am tired I don't want to
wait for the cable column I'm out of
here you skip your hip abduction work
then these bands are going to be a great
thing and do three sets of 20 band
standing hip abductions and tell me it
doesn't light up your upper glutes your
glute Medias like I've had big
bodybuilding Bros do that and it's so
funny if you can get a big bodybuilding
bro to do this he will be sold the
problem is they won't do it they won't
even put a band on and try it but that
does not stop them from forming an
opinion about it it's bizarre and with
bands you can do so much volume because
these exercises virtually create minimal
to zero muscle damage if you're willing
to train every day you could do bands
almost every day and see great results
because you don't have to use any of the
body's energy resources for repair it
all goes towards hypertrophy it might be
less efficient but if you're willing to
put in the work it is effective now next
up we've got the constrained
neuromuscular Duality hypothesis now I
made that term up sounds great doesn't
it this theory was created by coach kasm
Hansen it's very logical and I do think
there's a little bit of truth to it
which I'll explain later and what he
said was that your brain your nervous
system is not going to be able to create
maximum hip abduction torque and hip
extension torque at the same time too
complicated it's got a toggle between
the two tests and what you're left with
is going to be submaximal hip abduction
and submaximal hip extension torque
they're going to fight against each
other and you're better off doing each
joint action individually if you want to
grow the glutes just do hip thrust
without a band if you want to hit the
glut medius then just do band staining
hip abductions or glut medius Kickbacks
whatever but that's not evidence-based
the research does not support that
currently and I'll dive into that more
in a minute and the last explanation is
the scarcity mindset set when people
assume others are making a lot of money
it gets them very angry they get very
jealous for example in my situation Bret
contr owns BC strength he sells glute
Loops he's making a killing on these so
I'm going to bash them because I don't
like Bret KRA making money or they're
just just trustful of any science
pertaining to a product that you can
purchase because they suspect fraud or
bias and I understand that cuz that does
exist in our industry I mean you can see
ads that are so silly it's embarrassing
but every once in a while the science is
legit the equipment companies aren't
just trying to sell you product the
researchers investigating the topic are
not paid off they're not biased they're
not getting Kickbacks so I talked about
the five different reasons but I'm going
to dive a little bit more into this
constrained neuromuscular Duality
hypothesis because it's the most
interesting so the theory goes like this
when you're doing like a maximum squat
you're squatting to failure you're doing
a maximum load you need all your focus
to go on hip extension if you're also
pushing outwards while pushing upwards
the neural drive has to be
divided right like that does make sense
but the glutax is very interesting okay
so the upper fibers are more abductors
in the frontal plane right but what
happens when you lean forward or sink
down towards the bottom of the squat now
the middle and lower fibers are in a
better position to produce abduction
torque so they're producing abduction
torque in the transverse plane like if
you're doing a leaning seated hip
abduction makes sense that more of the
bulk of the glutax is going to carry out
hip abduction and when you do a squat or
a hipos the hip moves through a large
range of motion okay so when you're at
the top of a hip thrust and you push out
theoretically that would Target the
glute medius but the Kenny study showed
that it that did not in fact take place
when you're at the bottom of a squat or
a hip thrust in deep hip flexion you
can't send a lot of neural drive to the
glutes for some reason we don't
understand yet it could be related to
the neuromechanical matching principle
some evidence shows that the adductor
Magnus has the best leverage in deep hip
flexion whereas the glute Max has the
best leverage in full hip extension so
this Theory would imply that in the
bottom of a squat the brain the central
nervous system is going to prioritize
sending its drive to the adors it's
going to limit what it sends to the
glute Max because the glute Max doesn't
have good leverage there it can't
produce a ton of meaningful torque in
that position and then as you rise up
the glute Max gets more and more
involved and when you reach full hip
extension the neural drive to the
adductors has diminished a lot and the
neural drive to the glutes is maximized
for example at the top of the hip thrust
and there is some good evidence to
support this principle but it could also
be some sort of protective mechanism or
some reflex we don't quite understand
yet there are other muscles that don't
get activated well in the stretch
position for example the erector spine a
in fact there's a phenomenon called the
lumbar flexion relaxation phenomenon to
explain this you're still creating
torque but it's passive torque it's
generated by the elastic Force just
stretching of the muscle without it
being activated still produces torque
but it's probably going to limit the
hypertrophy stimulus because for maximum
hypertrophy to occur you would want
maximum activation in the stret
theoretically that's going to Signal
Titan and maybe some other mechano
receptors to drive the hypertrophy so
when a muscle's not activated Titan is
not going to do its thing it's probably
not going to be connected to actin it's
not going to get as much stretch so
that's going to be less signaling so a
couple years ago I did a really cool
experiment I don't know why I didn't
publish it I took 13 highly trained
lifters very strong women from my glute
Squad what I had them do is they got
down to the the bottom of a squat okay
now I could have used the Smith machine
but I knew that people are so silly they
would have said well that's on a Smith
machine so I used a barbell but it's not
moving I load it with such heavy weight
that they can't move it so yeah it would
have been the same in the Smith machine
but I just knew people would be like
they wouldn't be able to understand this
the same thing so I had my squad members
get to the bottom of the squad as deep
as they could go without rounding their
low back and they pushed up as hard as
they can now from that exact same
position I blocked their knees on both
sides and I had them in that same bottom
squat position push out as hard as they
can I also have them get on the seated
hip abduction machine and mimic their
squat posture same angle of hip flexion
same knee width and level of hip
abduction now I had electrodes on their
glute medius and then also their upper
middle and lower glutitis Maximus and
what I found was at the bottom of the
squat pushing upwards you got very low
levels of gluteal activation as soon as
you stopped trying to push upwards and
instead pushed outwards as hard as you
can same muscle lengthes same joint
angles same muscle length same level of
stretch glute activation soord doubled
or tripled in all of the regions lower
glute Max middle glute Max upper glute
Max and glute medius and on the seated
hip abduction machine the glute
activation at all four positions was
nearly identical so for this reason I
hypothesize that wearing a ban around
the knees but only focus on driving out
at the very bottom could be very
beneficial because that's the point
where you get the most stretch so more
activation with the same stretch should
lead to Greater hypertrophy I've done
other EMG experiments on myself where I
get down to the bottom of squat and I
cave my knees in and I try to
consciously activate my glutes as hard
as I can I can't even get to 10% of Max
glute activation but then when you stand
up and get your preferred stance for me
it's a little abducted feet turned out a
little bit and squeeze your glutes from
a standing position as hard as you can
you'll feel your feet turning out you'll
feel your pelvis poster your tilt and
you will literally get like 12 times
higher glute activation from that
position and since there's research
showing that you can grow a muscle by
just stretching it passively and you can
also grow a muscle by just putting
electrodes and using electric muscle
stimulation so stretch is just passive
with no activation and electric muscle
stimulation EMS is just activation with
no stretch so since muscle can grow both
ways I believe there are at least two
different mechanisms of tension driven
hypertrophy one that's active in nature
and one that's passive in nature so I'd
love to see an EMG hip thrust study
using a little bit lighter loads than a
f Max maybe like a 12 RM and then with
the cue of break the band when you reach
the bottom of the movement I think you'd
see an even greater difference of glute
Max activation compared to the no band
condition and this could theoretically
maximize glute hypertrophy while
simultaneously minimizing adductor
activity in and hypertrophy but this is
all theoretical we need experiments we
need hypertrophy research at this point
there is a logical basis for it though
and what we need to figure out is what
is the right combination of hipex
extension load versus hip abduction load
meaning what load to put on the back
during squats what load to put on the
hips during hip thrust or glute bridges
in combination of what band tension not
just what size band like the
circumference of the band but also the
strength and it could vary depending on
the exercise obviously it varies
depending on the lifter and their
Anatomy but the EMG results could be
affected by the Q the experience of the
lifter the barbell load the strength of
the band and the effort the proximity to
failure so I hope this video inspires
research to take more look at that cuz
I'd love to see more studies so I made
this chart to summarize the research and
and I'll leave this up so when you wear
bands around the knees during various
hip extension exercises you can see with
the hip dust it does tend to decrease
your performance by around 10% you get
10% less load maybe if you use the same
loads you'll get you know a couple reps
reduced glute medius activity decreases
with hip thrust and glute Bridges but
glutitis Maximus activity increases
especially in the upper glute Max with
no change in Quad activity no change in
hamstring activity and adductor activity
was not measured it hasn't been measured
in any studies now just an interesting
observation with the glute Bridge
hamstring activity was slightly reduced
while wearing the banner on the knees
but it did not reach significant so I'd
like to look into that more with back
squats you'd think that you'd see a
change in performance you think it would
reduce performance but all in all based
on the research it looks like there's no
change now let's discuss this when you
do squats with a band you're not trying
to break the band you're not creting
maximum abduction torque what you tend
to do is just make sure the knees don't
cave in but you're not trying to
maximize abduction width or trying to
break the band when you do hip thrust
and glute Bridges though you are trying
to maximize abduction torque you are
trying to break the bands so that's why
I think it doesn't impair performance
with squats the way it does with hip
thrust and glute Bridges but I do want
to say some studies show a slight
decrement with squats some no change at
all and one study even showed
performance benefit a boost of one more
rep with the group that wore the band
with back squats you tend to see an
increase in glute medius activation
which is opposite of what you see with
hip thrust and glute Bridges with no
change in Quad and hamstring activity
and once again adductor activity was not
measured and finally I just want to
mention deadlifts and leg presses
there's no research on them deadlifts
people might assume well why would you
wear a band during deadlifts you're
never pushing the knees out during a
deadlift variation except with sumo but
you couldn't wear a band during Sumo
variations it would have to be so big
around but it also would interfere with
the arm path but here's the deal you
could wear a strong band and push out
without really abducting the knees and
it could theoretically slightly increase
glute activation and it could possibly
slightly reduce adductor activation
which would be desirable with many
females seeking to grow their glutes
without growing their legs now I'm going
to put a picture of the glutes up here
the glut medius and Minimus are very
similar in shape and fiber Direction the
glute medus is just bigger but those
mainly produce frontal plane hip
abduction now I do think if you do like
a seated hip abduction at a 90° angle
the posterior fibers would be activated
seeking maximum glute medius and Minimus
growth you want to do a variety of hip
abduction movements but the upper
gluteus maximus and lower gluteus
maximus clearly have a unique stinct
neural strategy the upper glute Max does
not activate the same way that the lower
glute Max does now the upper glute Max
appears to be better suited for frontal
plain hip abduction in fact when you do
frontal plane hip abduction you'll get
upper glute Max activation you won't get
any lower glute Max activation now the
upper fibers the lus Maximus are going
to produce hip extension frontal plane
hip abduction transverse plane hip
abduction hip external rotation and
postop pelvic tilt the lower glute Max
fibers are going to produce all the same
actions except frontal plain hip
abduction but the lower fibers appear to
be better suited for hip extension and
the upper fibers appear to be better
suited for abduction and posterior
pelvic tilt again we need more research
on this the only study looking at upper
versus lower gluteus maximus growth was
the Plotkin 2023 study and and it did
not match EMG activity you got higher
gluteus maximus EMG activity with the
hip thrust especially in the upper
subdivision but hipos and squats
generated the same level of glutax
hypertrophy in the upper and lower
subdivisions so we definitely need more
research on the topic and now I'm going
to wrap up with directions for future
research what we need to know as I said
earlier in the absence of longitudinal
training studies measuring glute
hypertrophy all we can go by is
biomechanical rationale these are
mechanistic studies investigating things
like EMG activity you know muscle
stretch things like that so in order to
be more confident and form a better
opinion on this topic we need more EMG
studies I'd like to see for example hip
thrust studies looking at different cues
the top of the hip thrust versus the
bottom of the hip thrust when you use a
band during hip thrust you can just kind
of keep pressure the entire time and not
really go crazy with the abduction
torque it's really hard to keep pushing
out on the way up and down throughout
the entire set so I think a better
strategy is to focus on a particular
phase for example the top of the rep or
the bottom of the rep or the concentric
Rising portion or the Ecentric lowering
Porche as I said earlier I think if you
cue them to push out as hard as possible
on the way down trying to break the band
as you get to the very bottom of the
movement I think that would be the best
strategy for maximizing glute EMG
activity and glute growth we need to
know that we need to look at hipt us
with a variety of loads all we have
right now is a 5rm we need to look at
lighter loads we need to look at adduct
EMG activity during hip extension task
while wearing a band cuz it might reduce
and if so that's huge we need studies
looking at leg presses and deadlifts we
need to look at Regional glute growth
upper versus lower glute Max activity to
see if bands preferentially grow the
upper glute Max so I've mentioned the
future research throughout this whole
video I'm not going to go more into that
so I'll just wrap this video up with a
summary so in conclusion right now the
evidence supports wearing bands around
the knees during hip extension exercise
knee bands reduce hip thrust and glute
Bridge strength by around 10% even with
the slider loads during thrust and
bridges knee bands increase upper glute
Max activation and match lower glute Max
activation knee bands increase glute Max
activity during squats in addition to
glute medius activity even when the
knees cave in a bit knee bands should
not be worn for the glut medius during
hip thrust they should be worn for the
upper glute Max as they decrease glut
medius activity separate glute exercis
should be performed to train the glut
medius such as glut medus Kickbacks or
glut medus hip thrust wearing bands
during hip extension exercise is done
for the glute Max not for the glute me
we currently don't know if knee bands
reduce adduct or EMG activity and
hypertrophy during squats hip thrust Etc
knee bands do not appear to reduce squat
performance yes I find this hard to
believe but two studies show this on
trained subject more activation plus
same range of motion which is the same
stretch should equal more growth we need
hypertrophy studies to verify this there
are currently no hypertrophy studies
involving knee bands during hip
extension exercises so we must rely on
biomechanical r rationale the
constrained Duality hypothesis
popularized by coach kasm despite being
very logical currently lacks support
from a theoretical hypertropic
perspective but it does have support
from a strength and force perspective
knee bands do not impact quad or
hamstring EMG activity during squats or
thrust interestingly hamstring activity
is slightly reduced during Bridges but
not significant and we currently don't
know if knee bands increase glute
activity during deadlifts or leg press
and the last and final statement right
now until a hypertrophy study is knee
bands during hip extension exercise
should be recommended for those who one
train glutes frequently for variety's
sake two seek to grow their glutes
without growing their legs and three
prefer lighter loads or feel markedly
better when using them so in conclusion
I'm open-minded to a study emerging down
the road saying that knee bands did not
lead to more hypertrophy but we don't
know that right now we do have greater
EMG activity with the same form and the
same range of motion that should lead to
more glute growth so if you like wearing
the bands block out the bro
and keep on thrusting and if you're a
researcher who's interested in this line
of research please contact me I'd love
to be involved that's a wrap I'm Brett
CIS aka the glute guy if you found this
video interesting please make sure to
hit like definitely leave me a comment
let me know how I'm doing and please
subscribe to my channel if you like
talking about glutes if you like
strength training and hypertrophy
science cuz that's what I'm all about in
2025 I plan on releasing a video every 5
to 7 days thank you for
watching for